□ 630-624-9699 | sbernasek@gmail.com | sbernasek.com | sbernasek

Overview

Data scientist with software and research publications in top academic journals, issued patents, and startup experience. Brings a unique blend of creativity, math and science literacy, and engineering pragmatism, all backed by strong python skills and a healthy dose of common sense.

Expertise includes:

- Building models to analyze and simulate complex processes.
- Developing analysis and simulation pipelines to support R&D efforts.
- Prototyping state of the art methods from the research literature.
- Hacking together creative solutions to a broad variety of problems.
- Bridging the gap between research, engineering, and business through effective communication.

Python projects:

- sbernasek.com/flyqma automated analysis of patch patterns in microscope images of the fly eye
- sbernasek.com/flyeye systematic measurement, analysis, and modeling of cell behavior in microscope images of the fly eye
- sbernasek.com/tfbinding simulation of cooperative binding events between proteins and DNA (cython)
- sbernasek.com/genessa exact stochastic simulation of large-scale chemical reaction networks (cython)

Skills_

 $\textbf{Python} \ \text{package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL \& open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, numpy, scipy, scikit-learn, statsmodels, etc. / matplotlib / cython / PIL & open-cvelor package development / pandas, scipy, scikit-learn, scipy, scikit-learn, scient / pandas, scient / p$

Engineering MySQL / Rest APIs / web scraping / jupyter / git / unix shell / latex / HTML & CSS

Data Mining statistical analysis / dimensionality reduction / clustering / image & text processing and analysis / visualization

Modeling stochastic processes / spatio-temporal dynamics / process simulation / toy model development

Machine Learning practical experience with classification & regression methods / basic familiarity with deep learning & pytorch (eager to learn!) **Research** algorithm & pipeline development / hypothesis testing / scientific publication / inter-disciplinary collaboration / software development

Education

Ph.D. in Chemical and Biological Engineering Northwestern University

2014 - 2019

- Dissertation combined data science and chemical engineering to explore how cells make decisions during development.
- Published in high profile academic journals including Cell and PLOS Computational Biology.

B.S. in Chemical Engineering • High Honors University of California, Santa Barbara

2008 - 2012

Experience

Data Science Consulting (part-time while traveling!)

Present

- Built a predictive model that helped a recruiting firm focus their ad spend on more probable hires.
- Automated PDF text+image analysis routines to save hundreds of hours of tedious labor.

Researcher at Northwestern University Evanston, IL

2014 - 2019

- Accelerated a popular experimental technique by developing a computer vision algorithm to annotate patch patterns in biological images.
- Discovered a cell decision mechanism by using computer vision and data mining to derive statistical insight from fluorescence microscopy data.
- · Developed a statistical mechanical model of transcription factor DNA binding and used it to show how the identified mechanism works.
- Discovered a surprising link between development and metabolism by modeling the emergence of developmental mistakes.
- Designed and built several open-source python frameworks to help the research community analyze and simulate various biological processes.
- Mentored junior students in formulating their own research. Helped teach university-wide programming & data science bootcamp.

Process Engineer at LanzaTech Chicago, IL

2012 - 2014

- Invented two patented processes for converting waste CO2 to valuable lipid products.
- Designed and built the company's core techno-economic process modeling framework.
- Worked closely with researchers and engineers around the world to circumvent bottlenecks in process scale-up.
- Collaborated with technology providers to identify complementary value streams, leading to corporate partnerships.
- Advised executives and investors with technical analysis that directly inspired major strategic decisions.